Guide to the Irving S. Olds Papers 1818-1963 MS 325
New-York Historical Society
Irving S. Olds papers
1818-1963
New-York Historical Society
Olds, Irving S. (Irving Sands), 1887-1963
MS 325
18.25 Linear feet in 11 record cartons, 2 flat boxes, and 1 oversize folder
This collection consists of the personal papers of Irving S. Olds, a former President of the New-York Historical Society. He led a notable life, as a clerk for Chief Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes, as a law partner at White & Case, as CEO of U.S. Steel, and as an avid supporter of the arts. The majority of this collection dates from later in his life, primarily from the late 1940s to the early 1960s. Although he was still involved with U.S. Steel and White and Case during those years, the majority of this collection consists of personal correspondence, personal records of his own finances and history, diaries outlining his daily activities during his retirement, and ephemeral items from his life. The earlier records consist of mostly personal matters as well, despite his abundant use of White & Case stationery.
Arrangement
Arranged into six series:
I. General Correspondence (1915-1963)
II. Business Records (1929-1948)
III. Diaries (1910-1962)
IV. Speeches & Publications (1940-1960)
V. Photographs & Ephemera (1907-1962)
VI. Subject Files (1818-1963)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials bequeathed by Olds, 1963
Related Materials at N-YHS
N-YHS holds about 600 prints and other material from Olds's collection: see Irving S. Olds Collection of Naval and Other Historical Prints and Related Papers (PR 47), 1587-1960.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 11 record cartons, 2 oversize boxes, and 1 oversize folder, all containing the personal papers of Irving S. Olds, a former President of the New-York Historical Society. He led a notable life, as a clerk for Chief Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes, as a law partner at White & Case, as CEO of The United States Steel Corporation, and as an avid supporter of the arts. His papers do not contain many records from his legal and corporate careers, and instead, are largely personal in nature. Those files that do relate to his firms are mostly related to social matters. His correspondence files date primarily from his retirement years, and include pleasantries between him and colleagues, friends, and institutions. There is correspondence about his and his wife's art exhibitions: Olds was a collector of naval prints, and his wife, Evelyn, used those prints as inspiration to paint trays and a variety of other objects. His business records consist of the records of three corporations of which he was part owner. His personal diaries provide a detailed insight into his day to day affairs, although again, nearly all of these date from his retirement. His speeches and publications are mostly preserved in duplicate and triplicate, and were given to many corporate and collegiate audiences. Ephemeral records consist of photos, awards, and news clippings. Lastly, subject files consist of miscellaneous personal records divided by topic, mainly his and his family's financial and historical records.
Biographical / Historical
Irving Sands Olds (1887-1963) was born in Erie, Pennsylvania, the only child of Clark and Livia Elizabeth Olds. Clark was an attorney, and Irving grew up in a wealthy household. Irving attended Yale University for his undergraduate degree, and graduated with a B.A. in 1907. He then continued on to receive a law degree from Harvard in 1910. Upon his graduation, Olds took a position as a law clerk for then Chief Justice of the United States Supreme Court, Oliver Wendell Holmes. In 1911, he joined the law firm, White & Case, which today, is one of the largest law firms in the world. In 1917, Olds became a partner, and remained as such until his death. He married Evelyn Foster in that same year, and the two never had children.
Olds was an important player in building White & Case's banking and corporate clientele through the 1910s and into the 1920s, including Bankers Trust, J.P. Morgan & Co., and the Foundation Company. After a stint in France after the First World War opening White & Case's Paris Office, Olds returned to the U.S. and became involved in the relationship between his firm and the United States Steel Corporation. In 1936, Olds was elected to the corporation's Board of Directors, and in 1940, upon the departure of Edward Stettinius, he was made Chairman and C.E.O. He ran U.S. Steel for twelve years, through the rest of the Second World War, and into the Atomic Age.
Olds was a noted philanthropist and lover of the arts. He urged the foundation of, and eventually led, the "Council for Financial Aid to Education," an organization which directed corporate donations to universities. From 1962 until his death in 1963, he served as President of the New-York Historical Society, and was a benefactor and board member of both the Metropolitan Museum of Art and Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts. He studied naval history and had published two works about the topic, "U.S. Naval History, 1776-1815" and "Bits and Pieces of American History." He collected Revolutionary War and Naval prints, and amassed a collection of over 1,000 items, many of which were donated upon his death to White & Case and the New-York Historical Society. In his limited free time, he took on a number of speaking engagements at universities, and he was honored with many accolades and honorary degrees.
After a period of declining health, Olds passed away in March 1963, and was interred at Woodlawn Cemetery, Bronx, New York.
Letters (correspondence); Diaries.; Speeches (documents); Business records.; Photographs.; Philanthropy.; Courtesy.; Manufacturing industries.; Law firms.; Olds, Evelyn Foster, 1888-1957; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964 -- Letters (correspondence); White & Case; United States Steel Corporation
- Series I. General Correspondence, 1915-1963; 5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains mostly pleasantries between Olds and his colleagues, friends, and the public. Letters are approximately split evenly between carbon copies of letters written by Olds, and original letters received by Olds. Although there are occasional references to U.S. Steel and White & Case, the correspondence is mostly personal in nature. There are a few letters to and from notable figures, such as former President Herbert Hoover. The bulk of the correspondence dates from the 1940s to his death in 1963, although there are letters of his that date back to approximately 1910. Most correspondents are not well-known, although any of note (either due to their historical prominence or substantial appearance within the collection) will be specified within the scope notes of each folder. At the end of the series, there are subject files which contain mostly correspondence with universities at which he was speaker or from whom he was receiving an honorary degree, and with museums regarding exhibitions he organized.
  Arrangement
  These materials remain largely in the order in which they were organized when they were received by N-YHS. They are arranged in primarily alphabetical order by correspondent or by subject. There are some exceptions to this, especially in the case of related letters from various correspondents that were filed together under a principal correspondent's name, as determined by either Olds or his assistant. Much of Olds's early correspondence exists in bound volumes organized by first letter of correspondent's surname or in some cases in bound volumes of materials pertaining to one correspondent.
  Although the alphabetized correspondence had maintained its rough original order, the folders in which they were originally stored have been lost, and upon the onset of processing, the correspondence was found in roughly sorted piles in various boxes. The folder arrangement here was created by the processing archivist but likely approximates the original organizational structure. The subject files are housed in the last box of the series. They were still in their original folders and, during processing, were rehoused into archival folders.
  - Correspondence, A (2 folders), 1945-1962 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence, B (4 folders), 1941-1962 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3-6)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence concerning Edwin Beinecke, Ford Foundation, Crotched Mountain Foundation, Williams College, Grolier Club, U.S. Naval Academy, Aetna Life Insurance Corporation, Carnegie-Illinois Steel Corporation, Hammermill Paper Company, Mary Buchanan of Mesilla Park, New Mexico, Columbia University, and American Antiquarian Society
  - Correspondence, Behrend, 1922-1945 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes correspondence regarding Ernst R Behrend, the President of the Hammermill Paper Company, who was a close friend of Olds, and had ties to Olds's childhood hometown of Erie, Pennsylvania
  - Correspondence, Boykin, 1938-1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes correspondence concerning Carolyn and Ancrim Boykin, and their daughter, Lynn. They appear to be friends of Irving.
  - Correspondence, C, 1921-1935 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    Bound file of early correspondence
  - Correspondence, C, 1936-1948 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, C (5 folders), 1941-1962 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11-15)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding Chase Bank, Office of Mayor Robert F Wagner, J.P. Morgan, Columbia University, Albany Institute of History and Art, Norman P Clement, Antiques Magazine, American Telephone and Telegraph Company, Association of A. Crawford Greene
  - Correspondence, D, 1921-1947 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    Bound file of early correspondence.
  - Correspondence, D (2 folders), 1940-1962 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2-3)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding Carrier Corporation, Dartmouth College, War Production Board, Union College, U.S. Naval Academy, Alexander Davidson, Jr. Books, American Hospital of Paris, and American Steel & Wire Company
  - Correspondence, E (2 folders), 1921-1962 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4-5)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding Charles Edison, J.P. Morgan, Encyclopedia Britannica, Elihu Club, and U.S. Treasury Department
  - Correspondence, F, 1920-1935 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, F, 1936-1946 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Foster, 1953-1960 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    Contains correspondence relating to Belle W. Foster and the El Sabino Ranch
  - Correspondence, F (3 Folders), 1904-1962 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9-11)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding California Institute of Technology, J.C Fox (one letter from 1904 about taxes), Hunter College, Sons of the American Revolution, Jackson Hole Preserve, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Harold Fabian, First National Bank of the City of New York, and American Red Cross
  - Correspondence, G (3 folders), 1945-1960 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12-14)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding Philip Goodwin, Bradley Goodyear, Antoni Gronowicz, Yale University's Office of the President, St. Luke's Hospital, American Express, University of Kansas
  - Correspondence, H (3 folders), 1942-1963 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15-17)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding University Club, American Red Cross, Joseph A Heckel of Americana Prints / Paintings, City National Bank and Trust Company of Chicago, Yale University, Consolidated Western Steel, and Museum of Fine Arts. Also includes a signed 1960 letter from former President Herbert Hoover, to his "old friend", Irving Olds.
  - Correspondence, H, 1928-1962 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding Frances Hereford, Minnesota Historical Society, NATO, Secretary of the Treasury George M Humphrey. Also includes correspondence to and from former President Herbert Hoover about his birthday.
  - Correspondence, Holmes, 1915-1938 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    Bound volume containing correspondence regarding Supreme Court Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes, for whom Olds clerked in the 1910s. There are only a handful of letters that predate 1930, and none of the correspondence is addressed to or from Holmes himself. Nearly all letters are pleasantries to and from law colleagues, with the overarching theme of the letters having to do with Justice Holmes in one way or another.
  - Correspondence, I, 1930-1960 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, J, 1946-1961 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding IBM, Trinity College of Hartford, Senator Robert A Taft, Architect Louis Jaeger, Senator Kenneth Keating, and Representative John V Lindsay
  - Correspondence, K, 1940-1962 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding New-York Historical Society and John Deere company
  - Correspondence, Knight, 1946-1962 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    Includes newsclippings, correspondence, and court documents related to Richard A Knight, a former lawyer convicted of libel.
    At N-YHS, see also: AHMC - Knight, Richard A. and the Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014).
  - Correspondence, L (2 folders), 1941-1962 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7-8)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding Yale Club, Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, Harvard Club, Smyth Manufacturing Company, and Harvard University
  - Correspondence, M (4 folders), 1946-1963 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9-12)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding Secretary of State Edward R Stettinius Jr, Smyth Manufacturing Company, John C Mitchell Naval & Maritime Books / Prints / Models, Attorney Gilbert H Montague, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania Justice George W. Maxey, Grolier Club, Library of Congress, Yale University, Professor Clarence W Mendell, Metropolitan Opera, and Professor Thomas Mendenhall
  - Correspondence, N, 1941-1962 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding the Central National Bank of Cleveland, New York University President Carroll V. Newsom, Newberry Library, Old Print Shop, Ford Foundation, Attorney General Herbert Brownell, and Senator Edward Martin
  - Correspondence, O, 1942-1962 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence concerning Yale University and University of Colorado Denver.
  - Correspondence, P, 1942-1962 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding Alfred Paine, Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission, and Parker Gallery of London
  - Correspondence, R, 1941-1962 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding Madame Romaine Robert and Richard Robbins.
  - Correspondence, S (5 Folders), 1933-1962 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4-8)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence concerning Wabash College, Sweet-Orr Co., Anne & Marion Smith, British Hungarian Bank, Sheffield Farms Co., and Embassy of the United States in London. Also includes the American Bar Association Journal from February 1938, and The Harvard Graduates Magazine from March 1931.
  - Correspondence, T, 1948-1952 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence concerning Pan American Airways, and the United States Flag Association
  - Correspondence, V, 1947-1962 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence concerning the National Council of Women of the United States, Colonial Williamsburg, Irving Trust Company, and Hammermill Paper Company
  - Correspondence, W (2 folders), 1941-1961 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - Correspondence, Y, 1958-1962 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, Z, 1941-1961 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, Unalphabetized, 1940-1962 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Unalphabetized (2 folders), 1940-1962 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1-2)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence regarding Legal Aid Society, Metropolitan Opera National Council, Sons of the Revolution, American Antiquarian Society, Morgan Library, Columbia University, and Cooper Union
  - Correspondence, Antiques, 1959 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Books - Review, 1952-1962 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Brigham Young University, 1955-1961 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Bryant College, 1946-1961 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Franklin and Marshall College, 1959 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Hofstra University, 1954 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Long Island University, 1954-1961 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Oberlin College, 1958-1959 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Swarthmore College, 1956 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Syracuse University, 1955 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, Union College, 1954-1955 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, University of Akron, 1959-1960 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, Wabash College, 1957-1962 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Williams College, 1959 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, Wilson College, 1953 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, Exhibit - Hawley, 1958 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 18)
    Includes but is not limited to correspondence concerning an exhibition of Evelyn Foster Olds's painted trays in Hawley, Pennsylvania
  - Correspondence, Exhibit - Mariners Museum, 1957-1960 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, Exhibit - Miniatures, 1933 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, Exhibit - Naval Museum, 1959 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, Exhibit - N-YHS, 1955-1959 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, Exhibit - Old Print Shop, 1957-1959 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, Exhibit - Peabody Museum, 1957-1958 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, Exhibit - Smithsonian, 1958-1960 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, Kai-Shek, Chiang, Madame, 1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 26)
    Contains a letter from Mayor LaGuardia to Olds, setting plans for a visit from Soong Mei-ling, also known as Madame Chiang Kai-shek.
  - Correspondence, National Fund for Medical Education, 1960-1962 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, New Jersey Historical Society, 1958-1963 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, Stamps, 1938-1948 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 29)
    Contains photo reproduction of a letter in German, dating from the Nazi era, about special stamps.
  - Correspondence, World War I, 1916 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 30)
    Contains materials such as a letter written to Olds's father discussing his mobilization to Camp Beekman, and letters from J.P. Morgan & Co. a few weeks later discussing his discharge, which they appear to have prompted, based upon their need for his legal expertise during the war
- Series II. Business Records, 1929-1948; 3.16 Linear feet
  This series contains record books from three corporations in which Olds had a financial stake during the early to mid 1900s. The businesses were incorporated in Delaware, although the full scope of their enterprise is somewhat unclear based upon the surviving documents.
  The series is arranged into folders which are ordered by the name of the corporation. The last two folders contain oversized books pertaining to two of the corporations and are stored in a separate box.
  - Emerald Isle Corporation, Minute Book, 1930 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
  - Emerald Isle Corporation, Checkbook, 1936 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2)
  - Emerald Isle Corporation, Account Book, 1930 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
  - Black Diamond Corporation, Tax Records, 1930-1941 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
  - Black Diamond Corporation, Tax Records, 1942-1947 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
  - Black Diamond Corporation, Miscellaneous Records, 1931-1947 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
  - Black Diamond Corporation, Checkbook, 1938-1947 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
  - Black Diamond Corporation, Account Book, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8)
  - Black Diamond Corporation, Account Book, 1930 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9)
  - Resolute Corporation, Tax Records, 1930-1939 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 10)
  - Resolute Corporation, Tax Records, 1940-1947 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 11)
  - Resolute Corporation, Checkbook, 1944 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
  - Resolute Corporation, Minute Book, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
  - Resolute Corporation, Account Book, 1929-1940 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
  - Resolute Corporation, Miscellaneous Records (2 folders), 1936-1948 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4-5)
  - Unknown Corporation, Checkbook, 1943 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6)
  - Emerald Isle Corporation, Stockholders Register, 1930 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1)
  - Black Diamond Corporation, Stockholders Register, 1930 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 2)
- Series III. Diaries, 1904-1962; 1.33 Linear feet
  This series contains personal diaries from throughout Olds's life. Most date from his retirement and those are very detailed. However, they are more of a schedule of his daily life than an insight into his inner mind.
  After the first folder, which contains an autobiography written about his past, the diaries are arranged chronologicially. The last folder contains two daily calendar booklets inscribed by Olds.
  - Memoir, 1962 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7)
    Contains an autobiography of Olds's life for "White and Case Records", written shortly before Olds's death
  - Diaries, 1910-1911 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 8)
    Contains two seemingly identical transcripts of Olds's diaries from the time in which he clerked for Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes
  - Diaries (2 folders), 1951-1952 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9-10)
    Contains a diary from Olds's trip to Europe in 1951, and a detailed diary of his daily schedule during 1952
  - Diaries (10 folders), 1953-1962 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-10)
    Contains very detailed diaries, outlining Olds's schedule of every day's events from 1953-1962
  - Date Books, 1904-1961 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 12)
    Contains one date book from 1904 and one from 1961
- Series IV. Speeches & Publications, 1940-1960; 1.08 Linear feet
  This series consists of booklets of speechs given by Olds at educational institutions and corporate functions along with published booklets written by Olds about various political and economic matters.
  The majority of the items in this series were saved in duplicate or triplicate. All redundant booklets were separated into box 10 and are not intended for reading room use. The three folders in box 9 are organized by subject, and chronologically within each folder.
  - U.S. Steel, Remarks, 1940-1952 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1)
  - Political Remarks, 1944-1952 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Remarks, 1946-1960 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3)
  - Excess copies of speeches and publications, 1940-1960 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-3)
    Contains extra copies of a majority of the items contained in this series
- Series V. Photographs & Ephemera, 1907-1962; 1.38 Linear feet
  This series contains ephemeral material. This includes documents from throughout his life, such as passports. It also includes photographs that were found within the collection, various news clippings, certificates, and awards.
  The first part of this series contains photographs of Olds that are organized by subject. Immediately following, are various awards and ephemeral booklets. Ending the series are newsclippings that were amalgamated from throughout the accessioned material when no original order or context could be determined. There are five folders of oversize material in box 12.
  - Photos - Portraits of Olds, 1940-1953 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 4)
  - Photos - Cooper Union, 1956-1962 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 5)